Finding Aid for Center for Ethics in Public Life (University of Michigan) records, 2004-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Ethics in Public Life (University of Michigan) records 2004-2011
University of Michigan. Center for Ethics in Public Life.
2012095 Bimu 2
An extension of President Coleman's Initiative on Ethics in Public Life; the Center for Ethics in Public Life's goals were to promote discourse, research, and teaching on ethics at the University of Michigan. Includes records of the precursor initiative, ethics-related activities on campus, and the Center's administration under Dr. John R. Chamberlin from its creation in 2008 through its closing in 2011.
1.25 linear feet
9.35 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 10592 ) was received from the University of Michigan Center for Ethics in Public Life in July 2011. 10592
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Center for Ethics in Public Life records are restricted for twenty years from the data of accession under the University Executive Officers records policy.
The records includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Box 1 and digital files
In 2004, President Mary Sue Coleman established a task force to investigate various aspects of ethics in the context of education and scholarship. Acting on their recommendations, President Coleman launched the Initiative for Ethics in Public Life in 2005. The initiative sponsored a variety of public forums on ethical issues and provided funding in support of nearly fifty programs, workshops, and faculty research projects. Leadership of the initiative rotated on an annual basis; those serving included John Chamberlin (Ford School and Political Science, LSA) and Marvin Krislov (UM General Counsel) from 2005-2006; Derek Collins (Classical Studies, LSA), Joel Howell (Medical School and History, LSA), and Marvin Krislov (UM General Counsel) from 2006-2007; and Derek Collins (Classical Studies, LSA) and Susan Goold (Medical School, Bioethics Program) from 2007-2008.
In 2008, continuing to build on the findings and recommendations of the task force, the University of Michigan's Center for Ethics in Public Life (CEPL) opened its doors, with John Chamberlin as director. The objectives of the Center for Ethics in Public Life were to provide opportunities for discourse and education on ethics related issues, to provide funding and opportunities for research in ethics, and to be a resource for the community, with particular emphasis on the undergraduate student body and use of an interdisciplinary approach. The CEPL met these objectives by establishing a grant program, offering fellowships, hosting forums and other programs, and working with course development to include or highlight classes with ethics in the curricula.
The CEPL also formed several student organizations, including Students for Ethics, the Michigan Ethics Bowl Team, and the Michigan Ethics Union, as part of its effort to encourage discourse. A further effort to provide such opportunities was participation in planning a themed semester for the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts in 2010.
In 2011, as the university faced a shrinking budget, the decision was made to close the Center for Ethics in Public Life. After three years in operation, it was felt that the CEPL had achieved its goals, and that discussion and awareness of ethics had become embedded in the campus community and would continue as the University moves forward.
The Center for Ethics in Public Life collection has eight series: Presidential Initiative on Ethics in Public Life, Activities, Administration, and Archived Website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Center for Ethics in Public Life.; Ethics--Study and teaching (Higher)--United States.
Genre Terms:
Chamberlin, John R.
- Presidential Initiative on Ethics in Public Life (EinPL)
  The Presidential Initiative on Ethics in Public Life series documents the planning, development, and activities of the Center for Ethics in Public Life's precursor organization. It includes minutes and agendas and the Task Force Report produced for President Coleman as part of the initiative. The series not only documents the progress of the initiative from its instigation but also contains records pertaining to the establishment of the Center for Ethics in Public Life in 2008. Additional information on the Ethics in Public Life Initiative (EinPL), may be found in the Administration series (see the "Historical Files", part of the "Operations" digital content).
  - Center for Ethics in Public Life Background 2006-2009 (includes photographs on CD) (Box 1)
    [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2031 ]
  - EinPL Academic Integrity Subcommittee 2006 (Box 1)
  - EinPL Contact Information 2004-2008 (Box 1)
  - Ethics in Public Life Work Group 2008 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes 2009 (Box 1)
  - Task Force Report 2005 (Box 1)
- Activities
  The Activities series, 2005-2011, documents various activities taking place at the University of Michigan's Ann Arbor campus relevant to ethics. Among these activities are forums and other programs, including those sponsored by the Center, student organizations focused on ethics, and courses with an ethical emphasis. The series also contains records of the Center's involvement with the Fall 2010 College of Literature, Science, and the Arts's theme semester, "What Makes Life Worth Living?" Posters in the series promote a variety of events sponsored by the Center or other units. Please refer to the "Operations" section of the Administration series for digital materials that relate to various Center activities (including the Michigan Ethics Bowl Team, Bioethics Colloquia, seminars, forums, and Fall 2010 theme semester, among others).
  - Campus events and programs
    - A2ethics.org 2008 (Box 1)
    - AACU Core Commitments Proposal 2006 (Box 1)
    - Advisory Committee on Labor Standards and Human Rights Report 2008-2009 (Box 1)
    - Association for Practical and Professional Ethics (APPE) 2006-2011 (Box 1)
    - BBA Mentorship through Networks, Ethics, Teaching, and Service (BBA M-NETS) 2009 (Box 1)
    - Bioethics Colloquium 2010 (Box 1)
    - Bioethics Program 2009 (Box 1)
    - CEPL Sponsored Forums and Events, 2008-2011, 1 optical disks DVD (Box 1)
      (includes DVD of Spotlight Theatre Troupe Skits)
    - The Choice -- Ethics Blog 2006-2008 (Box 1)
    - Delta Gamma 2008-2011 (Box 1)
    - Ethical Compass 2007 (Box 1)
    - "Ethics and Professionalism: What Does a Resident Need to Learn?", Susan Dorr Goold and David T. Stern 2008 (Box 1)
    - Ethics-Related Courses 2005-2009 (Box 1)
    - Ethics Related Forums & Events, Non-CEPL Sponsored 2008-2009 (Box 1)
    - Honest Abe 2008 (Box 1)
    - John Chamberlin 2008-2009 (Box 1)
    - LS&A Academic Judiciary Committee 2008-2009 (Box 1)
    - LS&A Honor Council (Box 1)
    - Michigan Ethics Bowl Team (MEBT) 2009-2010, 1 optical disks DVD (Box 1)
      (includes DVD of meet)
    - Michigan Ethics Union (Box 1)
    - National Conference on Ethics in America 2009 (Box 1)
    - Project for Scholarly Integrity in Graduate Education Application 2008 (Box 1)
    - Provost's Seminar on Teaching (PSOT) 2006 (Box 1)
    - Students for Ethics 2006-2008 (Box 1)
  - LSA Theme Semester: "What Makes Life Worth Living"
    - Courses 2010 (Box 1)
    - Events 2010 (Box 1)
    - Peace Corps 2010, 1 optical disks DVD (Box 1)
      (includes DVDs of guest speaker Paul Theroux)
    - Planning 2010 (Box 1)
    - Postcards 2010 (Box 1)
    - Proposal 2008-2009 (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook, "What Makes Life Worth Living" 2010-2011 (Box 1)
    - Winners of: Student Reflections on the Theme 2010 (Box 2)
    - "What Makes Life Worth Living" Posters 2010 (Box 2)
  - Posters for various CEPL events 2010 (Box 2)
- Administration
  The Administration series, 2002-2011, consists of records documenting the administration of the Center and its programs along with grant proposals and fellowship program records. The series includes a large volume of digital materials from the office of Director John Chamberlin related to the Center's "Operations." These digital files include content created and maintained by staff members as well as a directory of Chamberlin's topical files and personal copies of material (JRC Files). The digital materials deal extensively with the administration of the Center, but also include "Historical Files" related to the Presidential Initiative on Ethics in Public Life as well as planning and publicity materials from various Center activities (including the Michigan Ethics Bowl Team, Bioethics Colloquia, seminars, forums, and Fall 2010 theme semester, among others). While there is some overlap with the paper collection, the digital material includes unique information, with video and image content in addition to Office files and still images.
  - Fellowship Program
    - Doctoral Fellowships 2009 (Box 1)
    - Fellows Program Development 2009-2010 (Box 1)
    - Postdoctoral Fellowship 2010 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate Fellows 2009-2010 (Box 1)
  - Grant Proposals
    - Fall Program Grants 2009 (Box 1)
    - Funding Program (Box 1)
    - Funding Recipients 2006-2008 (Box 1)
    - Program Grants 2010 (Box 1)
    - Program Grants 2011 (Box 1)
    - Program and Research Grants 2008, 2008-2010 (Box 1)
    - Research Grants 2009 (Box 1)
    - Summer Program Grants 2009 (Box 1)
    - Winter Program Grants 2009 (Box 1)
  - Operations
    - Annual reports 2008-2011
    - Association for Practical and Professional Ethics (APPE) circa 2009
      (Documents related to the involvement of John Chamberlin and the Center with the APPE)
    - Bioethics 2010
      (Planning and publicity materials for the First Annual U-M Bioethics Research Colloquium; includes additional materials for a Colloquium on Teaching the Moral Content of Professional Practice, cosponsored with the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching)
    - Closing the Center 2011
      (List of CEPL groups, events, and degrees that needed to be reassigned within the University following the Center's closing)
    - Courses 2009-2010
      (List of courses related to ethics across U-M schools and colleges; includes a proposal for the development of a course on professional ethics submitted to the Multidisciplinary Learning and Team Teaching Program.)
    - Doctoral fellows 2010
      (Publication, "A Role for Moral Vision in Public Health," by CEPL doctoral fellow Daniel Rubin.)
    - Ethics bowl team 2009-2010
      (Applications, publicity materials, competition cases, and budget information from the Michigan Ethics Bowl Team)
    - Events 2008-2011
      (Contains logistics, planning, and publicity materials for events sponsored by the CEPL)
    - Executive Committee 2008-2010
      (Meeting agendas, minutes, and materials from meetings of the CEPL Executive Committee)
    - Film series 2011
      (Promotional materials for the CEPL Winter 2011 film series)
    - Financial 2008-2011
    - Funding 2008-2011
      (Information on doctoral and undergraduate fellowships as well as student applications with essays.)
    - Historical Files (Ethics in Public Life Initiative) 2004-2008
      (Meeting agendas, minutes, and supporting materials as well as various reports, press release, and promotional materials related to the Presidential Initiative on Ethics in Public Life. Includes files collected by Project Specialist Lisa M. Jeffreys)
    - JRC Files: Director John R. Chamberlin's files 2004-2011
      (Files collected, created, and maintained by John Chamberlin; some material is duplicated in other directories.)
      - 2009 Doctoral Summer Fellows
      - Academic integrity
      - Association for Practical and Professional Ethics (APPE)
      - Articles
      - "Bending the Rules: Gamesmanship in Sports" (forum)
      - Bioethics colloquium
      - Budget
      - Codes of ethics
      - Collaborations
      - Curriculum
      - Debt reduction
      - Development
      - E-Newsletters
      - Ethics bowl
      - Event planning
    - JRC Files: Director John R. Chamberlin's files 2004-2011 (cont.)
      - Executive Committee
      - Fellowship programs
      - Forums
      - Funded projects
      - MBA Oath Program
      - Photos
      - Planning
      - Post Doc
      - Professional ethics
      - Research
      - Summer seminars 2010
      - Sustainability
      - Theme semester
      - UG (Undergraduate) fellows
      - Website
      - WG (Ethics in Public Life Work Group)
    - Marketing 2008-2011
      (eNewsletters documenting activities and events of the Center)
    - Media
      - Pictures 2009
        (Images of Ethics Bowl competitions, Center Director John Chamberlin, and other individuals and events associated with the CEPL.)
      - Video
        - Eleventh Annual Central States Regional Ethics Bowl at Marian University, Indianapolis, IN 2009
        - Spotlight Theatre Troupe Ethics Skits 2006
        - Images of original DVD cases 2006, 2009
    - Theme Semester 2010
      (Planning and promotional materials for various events during the LSA Fall 2010 Theme Semester, "What Makes Life Worth Living?")
    - UG (Undergraduate) Fellows 2009-2011
      (Video footage and reports produced by undergraduate fellows)
      [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2031 }
- Archived Website
  The Archived Website series, 2010-2011, documents the mission, activities, policies, and individuals involved in the operation of the Center for Ethics in Public Life. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as reports and administrative documents), and information about committees, initiatives, and events. This archived website is hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Archived Center for Ethics in Public Life website 2010-2011